<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="diaries.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<!--https://archive.org/details/mms_221/page/n67/mode/1up image 68ff.  -->

<journal xmlns="http://UW-LIS-diaries/ns/1.0">

    <metadata>
        <sourceInfo>
            <title>Emma Wormwood diaries, 1895-1898</title>
            <author>Emma Wormwood</author>
            <publisher/>
        </sourceInfo>
        <revisions>
            <change when="2022-05-12" who="EM">Started stub file</change>
            <change who="AP" when="2024-05-04">added markeup</change>
            <change who="AP" when="2024-05-30">added markeup</change>
        </revisions>
    </metadata>

    <!-- This extract is pages 3-10 of Emma Wormwood's diary, written in 1896. She was a school teacher in Illinois. The digitiized pages and crowdsourced transcription may be found here:  https://archive.org/details/mms_221/page/n67/mode/1up This begins at page image 68
   Wormwood mentions a lot of names of students and acquantances, book and song titles. She also quotes bits of conversations. -->
    
    <entries>
        <pb n="p01">Page 1</pb>
        
        <entry xml:id="e18960128">            
            <date when="1896-01-28">January 28th. Tuesday.</date> 
            <p>Got up early. <weather quality="pretty" temp="thaw">Pretty day, – thawed considerably</weather>. Had full school. Good lessons. 
            After supper had discussion on "Negro" and "Indian" question. Laughed about <name>Dollie</name> and me goin' (Gowin). 
            <name role="student">Roy</name> ate an onion, and I went in the other room and drew map of <place country="Italy">Italy</place>. 
            <weather quality="pretty" temp="cool">Beautiful night, not very cold</weather>. Went to bed early. I rode home from school, 
            <name>Jennie Dyer</name> and I stood up.</p>
        </entry>

        <entry xml:id="e18960129">
            <date when="1896-01-29">January 29th. Wednesday.</date> 
            <p><weather quality="pretty" precip="none">Pretty day</weather>. Had good school. <name role="student">Lou</name> went home at 
            last recess. They laughed about "<name><sobriquet type="nick">Scratch</sobriquet></name>" bringing <name>Rose</name> home. 
            A. class drew map of <place country="Italy">Italy</place>, on board. In B. Geog. I asked 
            how high is the <info source="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denali">highest peak</info> in 
            
            <pb n="p02">Page 2</pb>
            the <place country="United States">U.S.</place>, and had to laugh. We walked to meeting at the 
            <info source="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baptists">Baptist</info> church. <name role="preacher">King</name> preached about 
            <quote type="text">"The light of the world."</quote> Three boys went forward. I got letter from <name role="acquaintance">Miss 
            Riefenberg</name>.</p>
        </entry>

        <entry xml:id="e18960130">
            <date when="1896-01-30">January 30th. Thursday</date> 
            <p>Had good school. <weather sky="partial">Sunny in the morning – clouded in afternoon</weather>. At noon <name role="student">Irwin</name> 
            and <name role="student">Roy</name> tried to see who could act the "biggest monkey." Rode horse, rubbed him down, 
            <info source="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Skipping_rope">jumped rope</info> 
            (buggy line) and so-forth. <name role="student">Lou</name> and <name>Lillie</name> fixed minutes of last evening Society
            <alternates><abbr>met.</abbr><expan>meeting</expan></alternates> – Turned <name>Lillie</name>'s watch back with mine. 
            – <name>Jesse</name> laughs at me about being always hungry. <name>Nellie</name> and <name>Mary</name> went to church. 
            <name><sobriquet type="initial">J</sobriquet></name> called us "<sobriquet type="epithet">Back woodsers</sobriquet>" I replied, 
            that I would rather be 
                
            <pb n="p03">Page 3</pb> 
            a "<sobriquet type="epithet">backwoodser</sobriquet>" than a "<sobriquet type="epithet">heathen</sobriquet>". We went down 
            to the school house. Not many there; had no meeting. Went to <name>Mr. Strate</name>'s. Had music. Laughed at <name>Joe</name> 
            and <name>Charlie</name> about going to "Hunt"('s) <name>Charlie</name> has concluded he would rather Hunt than fish, so he's 
            not been lately seen going up the creek. – We suppose it is because the fish are all "Young." When we started home it 
            was <weather precip="rain">raining</weather>. <name>John</name> <name>Dollie</name> and I came across the pasture. (<name>Dollie</name> 
            thought we were going to <place country="China">China</place>.) <name>Joe</name> asked what I had been saying about 
            <sobriquet type="demonym">Kentuckians</sobriquet>. <name>Peek</name>'s brought <name>Mary</name> and <name>Nellie</name> 
            home. <name>John Whitehouse</name> was converted. (<name>John W.</name> came to school this evening for <name role="student">Lou</name> 
            and <name>Lillie</name>.</p></entry>

        <entry xml:id="e18960131">
            <pb n="p04">Page 4</pb>
            <date when="1896-01-31">January 31st. Friday.</date> 
            <p><weather precip="rain" sky="cloudy">Dark and rainy</weather>. Had twenty pupils. <name role="student">Irwin</name>, 
            <name role="student">Walter</name>, <name role="student">Charlie</name>, <name role="student">Roy</name> + <name role="student">John</name> 
            went down the road and came back after school had called. <name role="student">Roy</name> and <name role="student">John</name> 
            tried themselves. – I was doubly kind, in my actions, but, inwardly, I burned with anger. After school I traced pencil 
            marks in register. As I started, I asked if I had made any missteps, or done the least thing to cause such actions as had
            transpired. The reply, <quote type="dialog">"Nothing. Not a thing, they just took a notion to be mean."</quote> As I
            came across the bridge I sat on the banister and watched the water flow over the rocks. I read the <place town="Modesto">Modesto</place> 
            paper. <name>Jesse</name> tried to make us believe he could not read. After supper he brought up "scripture 
                
            <pb n="p05">Page 5</pb> 
            argument; read two chapters from the Testament, asked our opinions, then gave us his explanation. Calls us 
            "<sobriquet type="epithet">backwoodsers</sobriquet>." We went to bed early. <name>Lillie</name> did not come to school. </p></entry>

        <entry xml:id="e18960201">
            <date when="1896-02-01">February 1st. Saturday</date> 
            <p><weather sky="cloudy" quality="gloomy">Dark and gloomy</weather>. Wish I could be at <place>Nilwood</place> to the 
            Local Institute. I straightened up books and papers, put most of them in my valise. Had a talk with <name>Nellie</name> 
            about school. a perfect jewel, to be so good.) I fixed my tan skirt. <name>Jesse</name> went to <place town="Modesto">Modesto</place>. 
            <name role="student">Roy</name> cut wood. <name>Mary</name> baked all morning. (Had baked chicken for dinner, and I ate 
            so much dinner that I was not hungry for supper. <name>Jess</name> said it was the first time he ever saw me not hungry) 
            <name>Ed</name> came in the evening. He got letters from Mamma, <name>Ida</name> and <name>Katie</name> M. got school 
            journal and circular from <name>supt. McClure</name>. 
                
            <pb n="p06">Page 6</pb> 
                
            <marginal><illegible><trans who="EM">(Jermine)</trans></illegible></marginal> told about hauling one of my pupils around 
            in the big wagon. Laughed about him going to <place town="Carlinville">Carlinville</place> on Tues., following the wagon-ride. 
            <name>Joe</name> came home with <name>Jess</name>. Argued about "<sobriquet type="epithet">Back woodsers</sobriquet>" and
            "<sobriquet type="epithet">Mountain heathens</sobriquet>". They said <name>Dolly</name> got mad. The boys went to town. As they were
            starting, <name>Joe</name> was going to make me take back something; I made a certain remark which caused him to take sudden leave. 
            Gave us oranges. <name>Dolly</name> and I went to church with <name>Ed</name>. Roads were very bad, and we went through 
            the fields. <name role="preacher">Rhoads</name> preached, but got sick and <name role="preacher">King</name> took the meeting. 
            Excellent meeting. Got home about eleven. Boys came before we went to bed. After noon <name role="student">Lillie</name> came 
                to tell us about going over 
            
            <pb n="p07">Page 7</pb> 
            to <place town="Scottsville">Scottsville</place> to wait on her sick cousin. Wanted <name>Dollie</name> to take her part in the dialogue.
            Asked <name>Dollie</name> to bring her books. (Rocking chair proved to hold two)</p></entry>

        <entry xml:id="e18960202">
            <date when="1896-02-02">February 2nd. Sunday.</date> 
            <p><weather sky="cloudy" precip="rain">Rainy and dark</weather>. <name>Jess</name> went away. <name>Charie Crawford</name> came. 
            I read story of <title>"Howard and his Teacher"</title>. Laughed about "Love in the Kitchen"; also "Love in the Front-room." 
            ("I'd get it and keep it".) <name role="student">Roy</name> and I took down items; and <name role="student">Joe</name> started 
            for the book, I screamed, jumped straight up and ran in the bed room. threw the book to <name role="student">Roy</name> 
            but <name role="student">Charlie</name> got it. They went in little bed room to read but we would not let them alone: they went 
            out by the milk house and read, then gave us the book. <name>Mary</name> called on everybody to help put the hogs in the 
                
            <pb n="p08">Page 8</pb> 
            <marginal><name role="student">Irwin Baptist</name> is 16 years old today.</marginal> 
            lot. <name>Dolly</name> went to put <name role="student">Joe</name>'s hat on him and had to stand on the bench. Had dispute as 
            to whether pancakes were baked, or fried: proved that bake is right. <name>Jess</name> says <name>Flo</name> is the
            only good looking girl in <place usState="Illinois">Illinois</place>. <name>Mr. Essex</name>, the best looking man. 
            <place usState="Kentucky">Kentucky</place> is noted for tobacco, whiskey and and big feet. <name>Jess</name> says 
            "<quote type="dialog"><name>Dollie</name> is - is - is, all right.</quote>" "<quote type="dialog">She's too smart to 
            be called a <sobriquet type="epithet">backwoodser</sobriquet>.</quote>" <name role="student">Roy</name>, <name>Nellie</name> 
            and I are "<sobriquet type="epithet">Smart alecks</sobriquet>." I went to bed at seven o clock. <weather precip="snow">It 
                snowed,</weather> <weather precip="rain">rained</weather>, <weather precip="sleet">sleeted</weather> and what not, 
            all day. <weather>ground not at all frozen but covered with snow and sleet.</weather></p></entry>


        <entry xml:id="e18960203">
            <date when="1896-02-03">February 3rd. Monday.</date> 
            <p><weather precip="snow">Two or three inches of snow and still snowing. Trees and bushes look like Christmas trees. 
            Snowed all day, but thawed more than it snowed</weather> 
                
            <pb n="p09">Page 9</pb> 
            Had a very small school, only eleven. Stopped to see <name>Mr. Strate</name>. Made short talk about conduct of Friday. Better results, 
            but far from perfect. At noon, the girls were <info source="https://blog.nationalarchives.gov.uk/lock-love/">getting locks of 
            everybody's hair. (If you'll come over after school is out, I'll give you a lock of my hair.)</info> I was tired all day: about sick.
            After supper I wrote to mamma and to the girls. Talked of suicides. <name>Jess</name> said he had no sympathy for such people. 
            Would not grieve if his own father committed suicide. </p></entry>
    </entries>
</journal>
