<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="diaries.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="wwDiarySchematron.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>    
<!--https://archive.org/details/mms_221/page/n67/mode/1up image 68ff.  -->
<journal xmlns="http://UW-LIS-diaries/ns/1.0">
    <metadata>
        <sourceInfo>
            <title>Emma Wormwood Diary</title>
            <author>Emma Wormwood</author>
            <publisher>Newbarry Library</publisher>
        </sourceInfo>
        <revisions>
            <change when="2022-05-12" who="EM">Started stub file</change>
            <change who="AJ" when="2024-06-01">markup changes</change>
        </revisions>
    </metadata>

    <!-- This extract is pages 3-10 of Emma Wormwood's diary, written in 1896. She was a school teacher in Illinois. The digitiized pages and crowdsourced transcription may be found here:  https://archive.org/details/mms_221/page/n67/mode/1up This begins at page image 68
   Wormwood mentions a lot of names of students and acquantances, book and song titles. She also quotes bits of conversations. 
    -->
    <entries>
        <entry xml:id="xx1">
            <pb n="pb001"/>
            <date when="1896-01-28">January 28th. Tuesday. </date> <p>Got up early. Pretty day,
                –thawed considerably. Had full school. Good lessons. After supper had discussion on
                    <convo>"Negro" and "Indian"</convo> question. Laughed about <name>Dollie</name>
                and me goin' (Gowin). <name>Roy</name> ate an onion, and I went in the other room
                and drew map of <place>Italy.</place> Beautiful night, not very cold. Went to bed
                early. I rode home from school, <name>Jennie Dyer</name> and I stood up. </p>
        </entry>

        <entry xml:id="xx2">
                <date when="1896-01-29">January 29th. Wednesday.</date>
         
            <p><weather>Pretty day.</weather> Had good school. <name>Lou</name> went home at last
                recess. They laughed about <name>"Scratch"</name> bringing <name> Rose</name> home.
                A. class drew map of <place>Italy</place>, on board. In B. Geog. I asked how high is
                the highest peak in </p>
        </entry>

        <pb n="pb002"/>

        <entry xml:id="xx3">
            <date when="1896-01-31">January 30th. Thursday </date> Had good school.
                    <p><weather>Sunny in the morning – clouded in afternoon.</weather> At noon
                    <name>Irwin</name> and <name>Roy</name> tried to see who could act the
                    <convo>"biggest monkey."</convo> Rode horse, rubbed him down, jumped rope (buggy
                line) and so-forth. <name>Lou</name> and<name> Lillie</name> fixed minutes of last
                evening Society met. – Turned <name>Lillie's</name> watch back with mine. –
                    <name>Jesse</name> laughs at me about being always hungry. <name>Nellie</name>
                and <name>Mary</name> went to <religion aspect="meeting">church.</religion>
                <name>J</name> called us
                <convo reference="J">Back woodsers"</convo> I replied, that I <style
                    type="underlined">would </style>rather be </p>
            <pb n="pb003"/>
            <p> a <convo reference="J">"backwoodser"</convo> than a <convo>"heathen"</convo>. We
                went down to the school house. Not many there; had no meeting. Went to <name>Mr.
                    Strate</name>'s. Had music. Laughed at <name>Joe</name> and <name>Charlie</name>
                about going to <quote>"Hunt"('s)</quote>
                <name>Charlie</name> has concluded he would rather Hunt than fish, so he's not been
                lately seen going up the creek. – We suppose it is because the fish are all
                    <convo>"Young."</convo> When we started home it was <weather>raining.</weather>
                <name>John Dollie</name> and I came across the pasture. (<name>Dollie</name> thought
                we were going to <place>China</place>.) <name>Joe</name> asked what I had been
                saying about <place>Kentuckians.</place>
                <name>Peek's</name> brought <name>Mary</name> and <name>Nellie</name> home.
                    <name>John Whitehouse</name> was converted. (<name>John W.</name> came to school
                this evening for <name>Lou </name>and <name>Lillie</name>. </p>
        </entry>

        <pb n="pb004"/>

        <entry xml:id="xx4">
            <date when="1896-01-31">January 31st. Friday.</date>
                <p><weather>Dark and rainy.</weather> Had twenty pupils. <name>Irwin,</name>
                <name>Walter</name>, <name>Charlie</name>, <name>Roy </name>+ <name>John</name> went
                down the road and came back after school had called. <name>Roy </name>and
                    <name>John</name> tried themselves. –I was doubly kind, in my actions, but,
                inwardly, I burned with anger. After school I traced pencil marks in register. As I
                started, I asked if I had made any missteps, or done the least thing to cause such
                actions as had transpired. The reply, <convo reference="Roy and John">"Nothing.
                        <style type="underlined">Not </style> a thing, they just took a notion to be
                    mean."</convo> As I came across the bridge I sat on the banister and watched the
                water flow over the rocks. I read the <place>Modesto</place> paper.
                    <name>Jesse</name> tried to make us believe he could not read. After supper he
                brought up <convo>"scripture"</convo></p>
            <pb n="pb005"/>
            <p>argument; read two chapters from the <religion aspect="scripture theology"
                    >Testament,</religion> asked our opinions, then gave us his explanation.  Calls
                us "<convo>backwoodsers</convo>." We went to bed early. <name>Lillie</name> did not
                come to school. </p>
        </entry>

        <entry xml:id="xx5">
            <date when="1896-02-01">February 1st. Saturday</date>
                <p><weather>Dark and gloomy.</weather> Wish I could be at <place>Nilwood</place> to the
                Local Institute. I straightened up books and papers, put most of them in my valise.
                Had a talk with <name>Nellie</name> about school. (a perfect jewel, to be so good.)
                I fixed my tan skirt. <name>Jesse</name> went to <place>Modesto</place>.
                    <name>Roy</name> cut wood. <name>Mary</name> baked all morning. (Had baked
                chicken for dinner, and I ate so much dinner that I was not hungry for supper.
                    <name>Jess</name> said it was the first time he ever saw me not hungry)
                    <name>Ed</name> came in the evening. He 
<!-- this is written in the bottom margin of the page - the preceeding sentence continues on the next page. -->
                <margin where="bottom">got letters from <name>Mamma</name>, <name>Ida</name> and <name>Katie
                        M</name>. got school journal and circular from supt.
                    <name>McClure</name>.</margin>
            </p>
            <pb n="pb006"/>
            <p> told about hauling one <margin where="top">(Jermin?)</margin> of my pupils around in the big
                wagon. Laughed about him going to <place>Carlinville</place> on Tues., following the
                wagon-ride. <name>Joe</name> came home with <name>Jess</name>. Argued about <convo
                    reference="Joe and Jess">"Back woodsers"</convo> and <convo>"Mountain
                    heathens"</convo>. They said <name>Dolly</name> got mad. The boys went to town.
                As they were starting, <name>Joe</name> was going to make me take back something; I
                made a certain remark which caused him to take sudden leave. Gave us oranges.
                    <name>Dolly</name> and I went to <religion aspect="meeting">church</religion>
                with <name>Ed</name>. Roads were very bad, and we went through the fields. <religion
                    aspect="meeting"><name>Rhoads</name> preached, but got sick and <name>King</name>
                    took the meeting. Excellent meeting.</religion> Got home about eleven. Boys came
                before we went to bed. After noon <name>Lillie</name> came to tell us about going
                over </p>
            <pb n="pb007"/>
            <p> to <place>Scottsville</place> to wait on her sick cousin. Wanted <name>Dollie</name>
                to take her part in the dialogue. Asked <name>Dollie</name> to bring her books.
                (Rocking chair proved to hold two) </p>
        </entry>

        <entry xml:id="xx6">
            <date when="1896-02-02">February 2nd. Sunday.</date>
            <p><weather>Rainy and dark.</weather>
                <name>Jess</name> went away. <name>Charie Crawford</name> came. I read story of
                <quote cite="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harriette_Woods_Baker">"Howard and his Teacher."</quote> Laughed about <quote>"Love in the
                    Kitchen;"</quote> also <quote>"Love in the Front-room. "</quote>(<quote>"I'd get
                    it and keep it".</quote>) <name>Roy</name> and I took down items; and
                    <name>Joe</name> started for the book, I screamed, jumped straight up and ran in
                the bed room. threw the book to <name>Roy</name> but <name>Charlie</name> got it.
                They went in little bed room to read but we would not let them alone: they went out
                by the milk house and read, then gave us the book. <name>Mary</name> called on
                everybody to help put the hogs in the </p>
            <pb n="pb008"/>
            <!-- this appears to be written in the top margin -->
            <p>
                <margin where="top"><name>Irwin Baptist</name> is 16 years old today.</margin>
            </p>
            <p> lot. <name>Dolly</name> went to put <name>Joe's</name> hat on him and had to <style
                    type="underlined">stand on the bench.</style> Had dispute as to whether pancakes
                were baked, or fried: proved that <style type="underlined"> bake is</style> right.
                    <name>Jess</name> says <name>Flo</name> is the only good looking girl in
                    <place>Illinois</place>. <name>Mr. Essex,</name> the best looking man.
                    <place>Kentucky</place> is noted for tobacco, whiskey and big feet.
                    <name>Jess</name> says <convo reference="Jess">"Dollie is - is - is, all
                    right."</convo>
                <convo reference="Jess and Dollie">"She's too smart to be called a backwoodser."</convo>
                <name>Roy, </name><name>Nellie</name> and I are <convo>"Smart alecks."</convo> I
                went to bed at seven o clock. <weather>It snowed, rained, sleeted and what not, all
                    day. ground not at all frozen but covered with snow and sleet. </weather></p>
        </entry>

        <entry xml:id="xx7">
            <date when="1896-02-03">February 3rd. Monday.</date>
            <p>
                <weather>Two or three inches of snow and still snowing.</weather> Trees and bushes
                look like <religion aspect="holiday">Christmas trees.</religion>
                <weather>Snowed all day, but thawed more than it snowed </weather></p>
            <pb n="pb009"/>
            <p>Had a very small school, only eleven. Stopped to see <name>Mr. Strate</name>. Made
                short talk about conduct of Friday. Better results, but far from perfect. At noon,
                the girls were getting locks of everybody's hair. (If you'll come over after school
                is out, I'll give you a lock of my hair.) I was tired all day: about sick. After
                supper I wrote to mamma and to the girls. Talked of suicides. <name>Jess</name> said
                he had no sympathy for such people. Would not grieve if his own father committed
                suicide. </p>
        </entry>
    </entries>
</journal>
